software engineering radio episode 44
interview with Brian gets and David
Holmes
[Music]
welcome everybody to a new episode of
software engineering radio this is
another episode on concurrency however
it's not a normal episode it's an
interview episode with two people who
are quite famous in this area one is
Brian gets and the other one is David
Holmes both from Sun Microsystems and
we're going to talk about some advanced
topics of concurrency so welcome and
maybe let's start by introducing
yourself a little bit what you do what
you do for a living my name is Brian
gets I'm a senior staff engineer with
Sun Microsystems and I have been a
professional software engineer for the
past 20 years recently I've been doing a
lot of work in software education I've
over 75 articles on Java development and
most recently published the book Java
concurrency in practice which was the
best-selling book at JavaOne to our
great satisfaction and it's probably the
best reading book on concurrency I
really liked it thank you very much we
worked hard on it yeah and so we're here
at the oops oops law conference giving
several tutorials on concurrency as
we've done in past years and my name is
David Holmes I'm currently working for
Sun Microsystems and at this time I'm a
I'm an engineer in the hotspot vm
runtime group I've been teaching
concurrency in Java now for pretty much
10 years it started way back in 1996
when I shortly after getting a copy of
Douglass book on concurrent programming
in Java and you know there was a great
demand at the time for teaching people
about this this new language and and how
the threading model worked and various
others there are a lot of misconceptions
around in the early years and it was
something we thought would sort of pan
out in a couple of years everyone would
know how to do it when ten years later
West we're still teaching people and and
we've expanded things a lot with the jsr
166 concurrency utilities working on the
on the book to Java concurrency in
practice to get more information out and
you know I really enjoyed teaching
people how to make effective use out of
concurrent programming mmm-hmm so let's
let's look at some of the things we're
going to discuss everybody knows that
probably the most important thing in
concurrent
programs is to make sure they don't fail
in the sense that you have that locks
and so liveness is probably an important
thing so maybe let's start by discussing
difference between safety and liveness
and then discuss a couple of topics or
techniques how you can ensure liveness
well the basic safety verb for versus
live in a segment is very simple your
safety is to ensure that nothing bad
happens
whereas liveness is to make sure that
something does happen preferably
something good that actually has your
program achieving the result that was
intended yeah and these two design
forces are always in it that they're
always opposing each other because
typically are the things that we do to
make the program safe introduction of
locks they tend to impact on the
liveness because while things are locked
they can't be accessed concurrently that
means activities are delayed progression
is is affected and conversely every time
we try to improve liveness by removing
locks and doing things like that if
we're not extremely careful how we do it
we tend to introduce safety issues
because we remove a lock that should
have been present we now have concurrent
access to something and now we go from a
slow correct program to a fast broken
one and that is the key thing that we we
have to try to avoid hmm one of the real
challenges of concurrent programming is
that it fundamentally breaks the execute
the mental execution model we were all
taught we know those linked concurrently
that's right we think sequentially we
think in terms of this abstract von
Neumann system and that's a great
abstraction for teaching and we've all
internalized it quite well but in
reality the reality is quite different
and the so we're taught certain things
that can go wrong and we tend to think
of those as the range of possible
failure modes but in concurrent programs
there's many things that can go wrong
that can't go wrong in the sequential
program sequential program could have
liveness failures like infinite loops
but it can't have dead locks or live
locks or missed signals sequential
programs can have all sorts of safety
failures which we just call bugs but it
doesn't have race conditions and data
races so the range so everything that
can go wrong in a sequential program can
also go wrong in a concurrent program
and then there's a whole range of new
things that can go wrong many of which
are subtle and confusing and unfamiliar
and to top things off and make it even
worse the things that
can go wrong don't go wrong every time
yeah when a sequential program we're
used to we can write a test and if our
if the test passes we've developed some
confidence that our program is correct
and if it fails it fails repeatedly and
we're able to use that information to
debug it in concurrent programs failures
are much are usually rare probabilistic
events and that makes them much more
difficult to test for much more
difficult to reproduce and analyze
that's where the notion of a hisen buck
comes in right whether the act of
debugging something prevents the BOK
from happening absolutely and there is
and there are certain bugs that just
will never happen on an Intel system but
they'll have because Intel has a
stronger memory model than say PowerPC
and so if you do all your development
and testing on a Windows system you you
may not see certain failures that would
show up on other platforms so what are
some of the techniques that I can use to
prevent liveness problems to prevent
deadlocks any any like two or three
tricks or practices that people should
try to avoid not avoid to stick to some
of the key things with the liveness
deadlock is one that always comes to
people's mind because as soon as you use
locking and if you overuse locking you
end up invariably needing to acquire
multiple locks at a time and as soon as
you need to do that and you do it in the
wrong order then you can get a deadlock
so there are a couple of general rules
of thumb for for handling dead locks or
for avoiding avoiding deadlocks and the
general rule for avoiding deadlocks is
you have to acquire multiple locks you
always try to acquire them in the same
order if you do that then a deadlock is
impossible but imposing an absolute lock
ordering on things it can be done when
you have entire control over the program
and it can influence all of the code but
sometimes it it isn't always possible to
do that and of course if you're
developing a component and a light or a
library and that you know that you're
acquiring a lock internally and then
you're accessing some other object you
don't know exactly what's going to
happen in that other object and at one
point you've lost any any way to control
the lock ordering so one of the key
design rules for
for writing components and library
routines is to always try to avoid
holding locks when you call out into
other other objects other components and
this is what we call making an open call
the idea is that when you call out to
someone you don't hold the lock on the
current object so that object itself is
still open for receiving further
requests from other parts of the system
this not only improves the
responsiveness of the object that's open
but it makes it impossible to get a
deadlock by calling this other component
because you simply don't have the
multiple lock acquisition mm-hmm and
this illustrates the tension between
safety and liveness that David was
talking about many people when they're
first shown some of the things that can
go wrong in a concurrent program their
first reaction is oh well I'll
synchronize everything and I won't be a
problem and as a solution that's bad in
two ways one is that it's often not good
enough to get the correctness that
you're looking for but also
synchronizing everything means you're
requiring many more locks you're much
more likely to be acquiring multiple
locks at the same time and you're asking
for deadlock trouble yep and and so one
of the another way to think about how to
avoid liveness problems is to have a
global view of where am i doing things
that are going to require locking and
can I sequester them into some smaller
part of my program so I have less to
analyze in terms of locking behavior
okay so another topic that I think is a
little bit beyond what is probably known
to everybody which is probably
synchronized key word our synchronizers
things such as latches count down
latches sim force so can you give us
some overview of which kind of
synchronizes there are specifically then
in Java 5 and also generally yes so one
of the things that we did as part of the
jsr 166 expert group this was the JCP
group that specified the java.util
concurrent package is we looked at what
are the sorts of mistakes that people
make with concurrent programming and
what can we do to reduce those numbers
of mistakes and we identified that there
are a number of patterns that appear
over and over and over again and nearly
every concurrent program and so what we
did was encapsulate these pattern
in two classes and allow people to
specify what they're doing at a higher
level of abstraction providing them a
known safe correct building block and so
examples of these higher level building
blocks are things like Dijkstra counting
semaphore which is useful for bounding
the number of resources that you are
requiring or the number of activities
that are allowed to access a certain
resource latches and barriers that are
useful for allowing multiple parties to
coordinate to solve a problem if you
want to wait until a certain number of
players are ready to play and play a
game you need eight players for the game
and the players arrive independently and
say okay I'm here you don't care what
order they arrive in you care about when
when does the eighth player show right
and latches are a pattern that are used
to implement something like that and so
there's a countdown last class that was
at at the class library similarly
barriers are useful in parallel
iterative algorithms where you have
broken a problem up into some multiple
sub parts and each each thread is going
to go off do a little bit of work but
you want them each each thread to finish
step one before anybody moves on to step
two and so a barrier is a common pattern
used to implement this and so by looking
at how is it that people actually solve
concurrent programs what tools can we
give them to make it easier to organize
them so that they're less tempted to use
the low-level facilities provided by the
language which are error-prone and hard
to guess so when you're writing a
concurrent program there are two key to
key sides to the concurrent program one
is dealing with the safety issues as
we've said which is all about figuring
out your you your where your locks need
to go and what you need to do to protect
interference from happening on shared
data and then the second major thing is
identifying all of the activities in
your program exactly what the threads
are what the threads are doing and how
to coordinate them because the second
hardest problem is then coordinating the
threads for what they're doing
you have producer-consumer situations
where you have to wait for data to be
available before you can process it you
need threads to get to a certain state
before they can proceed with the next
phase of computer
there are many many different types of
coordination situations that arise in
programs but the fundamental
coordination protocol needed there can
be abstracted out into these
synchronizer classes so using simple
things like semaphores countdown latch
cyclic barrier exchanger is another one
exchanger allows pairs of threads to
meet together and an exchange data I can
it our wonderful kind of thing yeah
synchronize sorry exchange of very much
like a basic rendezvous mechanism for
two threads that slightly barriers are
on the rendezvous mechanism for multiple
threads these very simple abstractions
can be used to affect the communication
coordination protocol for a wide range
of applications so that you mentioned an
interesting term and that is protocol so
if you want to build concurrent
applications you have to agree on
certain protocols how the various
parties access resources and and the
problem is that compilers can enforce
these protocols is something you have to
get right by design or review and that's
probably one of the fundamental
challenges of building concurrent
programs yeah that's very true I mean
encapsulation is our friend here if we
can encapsulate the protocols inside the
objects that that need to enforce them
so locking is a good example locking as
a protocol if you have to rely on
everybody who accesses the object to get
the protocol right then you're asking
for trouble you have a fragile program
but if you can encapsulate all of the
ways to get to the shared state if it if
the shared state is well encapsulated
and confined within some higher-level
service object then the protocol is
enforced by the service object and
nobody can violate it communication
protocols are a little bit harder
because you would like to write the
activities themselves as a as their own
abstraction but then you have to
explicitly write the communication
between them and depending on how that
how the different activities are in are
being written and who's writing them you
know you may be able to come up with
certain you know handshake mechanisms
that you know producing consumers is a
good idea producers know that they just
have to shove a result somewhere and
consumers know they have to get a result
from somewhere and you know the
abstraction we use for connecting them
is just some abstract notion of a
channel or a chip
and that's as much detail as they need
to know about the mechanism but they
just need to know what the what the
interface to it is other things are a
little bit trickier
you know threads are involved in
parallel competition computation tend to
you know that they all know what's
happening and they all know that they
have to be agreed-upon points on where
they have to synchronize so depending on
the situation you you may have to
internally may be able to internalize
these protocols and sometimes there are
external ones it's the way that you
construct the application out of
different parts and you have to set up
the communication links between them yep
you already mentioned encapsulation and
I think a probably strong form of
encapsulation or maybe just a synonym is
a threat confinement so if you don't if
you don't give out or make resources
available to other state as you said
they they can't they can't violate the
protocol so we agree that that coming up
with the proper confinement of resources
to certain parts of the program is an
one fundamental way of designing thread
safe programs yes so the rule is in a
concurrent program that whenever two
activities access the same mutable data
they have to have a protocol for
coordinating their access to it
otherwise they may step on each other
and so there are three ways to
accomplish that one is don't share yes
if if only one thread ever has access to
the data then it doesn't have to worry
about anybody else stepping on its date
right and this is what we call thread
confinement and this is how subsystems
like AWT and swing in java achieved
their thread safety and for example like
for example parameters to stateless two
methods that don't access any members
are automatically thread confined so
that's would be one way of doing that
that that's right any any variable that
is local to a local to a method is
starts out its life as thread confronted
now you could violate that thread
confinement by publishing it in a shared
collection but as long as you don't take
any step to make it visible and publish
it to the heap where another thread
might might find it you can be confident
that that it's not shared so that's
that's what not sharing is one way of
doing it another way of doing it is not
mutating if you have to synchronize one
coordinate access to mutable state if
you don't modify the state
then you don't have to worry about one
thread modifying it and stepping on the
value that another thread is using so
you have sort of two ways to avoid the
hard part one is don't share the others
don't modify yeah and if neither and if
neither of those approaches work for you
then you have to fall back to the old
standby which is religious
synchronisation and that's hard to get
right for exactly the reason that David
was getting at is that we have to invent
protocols for coordinating access to
shared State it's not part of the
language the tools can't do not at all
the compiler doesn't enforce these
protocols and whenever you have multiple
activities coordinating together they're
going to have to agree on a way to work
together whether it be accessing data or
signally signaling each other when when
something has happened and if these
protocols are necessarily part of your
programs design and it's possible for
your program to violate its own design
yeah you said that one way of avoiding
these problems is not modifying stuff
immutable objects that reminds me of
functional programming so because it's
side-effect free right whenever you
change something you actually clone
something and then kind of apply the
changes so you create something new
would you say I mean it's kind of
suggestive question but so seems like
functional programming is a good way to
writing good concurrent programming
programs yes and that's that's one of
the areas where good object-oriented
design principles and good concurrent
programming principles are in agreement
another is what David just said is
encapsulation encapsulation is good for
writing single threaded programs and
it's even better for writing concurrent
programs and immutability is the same
the mutable objects are simple you can't
get them into an incorrect state you
can't violate their invariants you don't
have to worry about them changing
unexpectedly and so immutable objects
are simpler and now of course at some
point every program has some mutable
data otherwise it doesn't do anything
but if we can limit mutability to a
smaller set of well-defined places it
becomes much easier to ensure that yes
we're applying this the correct
synchronization protocol
everywhere where we access the shared
data and the smaller space that is the
easier it is to get your program correct
and one of the things that people often
don't realize about immutable data is
that you know that they tend to think
initially that well oh this doesn't
apply very often there's there's not
much immutable data I have I have
multiple pieces of state information in
my in my service and it's it's all
mutating mm-hm and so immutability can't
help me but that's not quite the right
way to look at it because we often if
you have a compound state within a
service or an object and you're exposing
that state through a series of simple
access or methods then what you're
actually exposing is an inconsistent
view of the object because you never
know whether the value of field a and
the value of field B that you've just
read as two separate operations whether
they actually reflect the same state of
the object or whether something has
mutated one of them in between between
yeah so often what you need to do in
these cases is actually group your stay
together you want to encapsulate a state
so compound object as a compound object
as a term at a split representation
right we actually want to represent that
state as a compound abstraction that we
can then present as an immutable
standard yeah an immutable snapshots of
state are a very useful and powerful
tool yeah okay we are we talked about
liveness before liveness is obviously
related to performance the more lively
your program is the better it performs
so I would probably think that too much
locking as we said before
makes the performance worse so what kind
of optimizations are there that maybe
you know compilers or anything can
optimize a way locks you're locking in
performance so I definitely interact and
one of the key things though is you know
that the issue is not so much the
locking is it's the contention if you
really have high contention in your data
then whatever mechanism used to protect
that is is going to cause a bottleneck
because the data is contended so the
data is is a bottleneck but if you know
when people start as brian said earlier
people who sort of led down the path of
naively locking everything and and you
can very easily reach situations where
you know you have so many levels of
locked it's like putting a padlock on
your bedroom door and having a padlock
on the door to the hallway and putting
another deadlock on the on the front of
the house and you know the street has an
armed guard at the end of it with a
large man
Gate and it's like everything is
perfectly safe but it's just a little
bit too much safety there there's a
there's a bit of overhead in trying to
deal with all that some of the things
that compilers are trying to do now to
be a bit smarter about some of the stuff
is la collision and lock coarsening and
la collision is basically removing locks
if the compiler can tell that an object
is actually thread confined it's good
example the early collection classes
vector and hash table were defined as
synchronized
election objects and yet 99% of the time
they're used in a thread confined way
our locking is completely redundant it's
useless now VMs have gone to a lot of
trouble over the years to learn how to
decrease the cost of uncontained add
locking so you get that almost for free
so the next step is to actually get it
for free if the compiler can tell that
the object is thread confined then
there's no locking occurs whatsoever and
they can do this using escape analysis
and this is something that's you know
the literature has been there's been a
lot of literature on escape analysis
over the years and a lot of research
languages have employed it for various
various types of system but it's finally
making its way into mainstream system so
that you know dynamic compilers in
runtime environments are trying to do
some of this escape analysis so that
they can do la collision and some other
forms of an hour's to do lock coarsening
that if you keep acquiring and releasing
locks in in a sequence of code that you
can actually remove the multiple lock
users and convert one single one yeah
which actually has it has a potential
impact on liveness so it's not something
you can do arbitrarily otherwise you
would just be tempted to remove all
locking and put a giant lock at the
beginning of everything and that won't
work so that there is a lot of that
there's a lot of research in this area
and heuristics I guess and yeah and a
lot of potential potential optimizations
for all of these over optimized cases
sorry over synchronized cases yeah
and and when speaking about performance
it's actually very useful to divide
performance into two separate components
and which often get conflated when
people discuss it there's performance
and scalability and these are actually
almost orthogonal measures so
performance is what we're used to
thinking about in sequential programs
how fast can I do this unit of work can
I do it in 10 milliseconds instead of 12
milliseconds scalability is a different
notion and it's a measure of how much
work can I do with a given amount of
resources and if I have more resources
available can I do more work right so
ideally if your program scales perfectly
if you throw 10 times as many processors
or systems and discs or network pipes or
whatever whatever
can I process 10 times as much work and
of course no program actually scales
ideally like that but there's certainly
some that do much better or much worse
than others and as multi-core processors
are becoming ubiquitous this is becoming
a much bigger deal a few years ago a
multi-way system might have had four or
eight processors and now we're starting
to see systems that can execute dozens
or hundreds of threads concurrently and
the degree to which exclusive resource
locks become a scalability bottleneck is
becoming much much more important now
another topic I'd like to get to is how
do I test concurrent programs you
already talked about the hyacinth
Heisenberg effect so if I write tests or
debug something they are that I'm trying
to get it it's not there anymore so I
mean what kinds of best practices are
there for testing concurrent programs
maybe except for hiring dhokli maybe
well that would certainly be an
excellent start the reality is the
testing concurrent programs is extremely
difficult for a number of reasons one is
as I said earlier concurrent programs
are more complicated than sequential
programs so they're harder to test the
tests for concurrent programs are
themselves concurrent programs and since
concurrent programs are harder to write
concurrent tests are harder right okay
and one of the problems especially when
writing performance tests is that the
test programs may in turn introduce
synchronization or timing artifacts that
perturb the behavior
the code being nested and so it's not
simply a matter of slapping the obvious
test routine around the the code being
being tested sometimes you have to work
very carefully to craft and unintrusive
test run tests for concurrent programs
need to run for much longer and explore
much larger percentage of the state
space but laws the errors you're looking
for are not simple errors like if I pass
null to this method it throws throws an
exception but it if this thread does
this and then this thread does that
before this other thread does that then
we'll get the wrong result and in order
to set up it interactions like that and
give them a chance to occur you have to
run for much longer and with a much
larger number of potential interleavings
and in some sense designing tests that
do this as a black art yeah one of the
ways to simplify the process is to limit
the concurrent interactions in your
system to a smaller part of your system
and so as David was talking earlier
about the producer/consumer pattern one
of the nice things about that is the
producers which are the activities
within your program that are finding
work to do all they have to do is they
don't interact with other producers
usually they find maybe they're crawling
a filesystem or they're crawling a
website and they're each working
independently they identify a bit of
work to do and they stick it on a work
queue to be processed and the only
concurrent interaction is between is
that part where the producer is putting
an element of a cube and similarly on
the other side the consumer is taking
elements off the queue and then likely
doing something with it that doesn't
involve interaction to other threads but
and so if you can structure your program
so that the concurrent interaction is
all there in the shared work queue now
you only have one thing to test you have
to test that your work queue works
performs correctly and fortunately there
are some excellent implementations in
the class library that have already been
tested to growth that you can use with
confidence and so by again sequestering
the concurrent interactions in your
program into a smaller area you have a
better chance of testing them and just
as with sequential programs though there
are two key style of tests with
concurrent programs black box white box
testing
so the key thing with black box testing
often people just refer to as stress
testing is that you're really just
exercising the external api's of an
object or a service and you want to try
and throw as much concurrency at it as
possible and you hope that it exercises
all the possible interleavings and
interactions that might occur now simply
doing that and hoping doesn't really
help because it it turns out that if you
run it on a particular platform your set
of possible interleavings is just a
small fraction of the theoretical set
and you know you'll get a different set
on a different type of hardware so there
are some tools that are that people have
been working on and I believe it's built
pure at the University of Maryland that
has a tool for interjecting arbitrary
interleavings of threads and code is
running so basically is if you if you
could if you could force a context
switch between any any pair of
instructions to actually generate the
very center leavings right now obviously
the number of possible permutations
there means it's impossible to compute
yeah but if you can introduce these
interleavings to some random degree to
get a much better coverage of what
you're testing and and the second aspect
is the actual white box testing which is
sort of more along the lines of what
Brian was discussing previously that if
you understand the the basic operation
of the protocols that you've coded up
and interactions you you can try to
formulate properties say if I get to
state X and this happens I should go to
state Y and the hard part of that is how
do you get to state X to actually
initiate the test yeah and that's
probably one of the still the biggest
outstanding challenges and you know we
tend to have to use a range of our own
tools and range of synchronizers when
we're testing so example thread pool
executor we need to use latches and
barriers and a range of other things to
try and force the system into a
particular state so that we can then
test the property of the executor that
we actually want to test and that's
extremely difficult to do and you know
we certainly could do with more research
and more tool development in this area
to try and verify and assist in saying
how do I get to state X so I can test
for the transition to state Y yeah and
and just a little bit of a plug here
there are some of these tricks that
David I was alluding to are described in
greater detail and in the testing
section of our book which as far as I
know
is one of the few places that actually
addresses ya explicitly in testing
concurrent programs yeah so how does the
Java memory model or more generally what
kind of support does the VM have to
provide for for concurrency we already
talked about lock removal as an
optimization technique what other
aspects are interactions are there
between concurrency in the Java memory
model so the Java memory model is an
abstraction that serves as several
purposes one is that it specifies a
least common denominator set of promises
that the platform makes to the program
and this facilitates the the development
of thread safe concurrent programs that
programs know that this is what I can
expect from the platform and if I code
to this my program is going to be
correct on all Java platforms now it's
also it's been designed not only to
provide a reasonable set of coherency
promises to the program but also to
enable VMS to optimize code in in in
sensible ways so there's a tension and
specifying a memory model the stronger
you make it the easier it is to write
programs but the harder it is for a VM
to optimize the program and do things
like what David was talking about such
as removing locks and were reordering
instructions so that they can execute
faster etc and so the the memory model
is something that a lot of programmers
will just never have to see your
especially if you fall if you use the
higher-level utilities that we've been
discussing and and use the usage
patterns that are you know they're
recommended these are designed to be
thread safe and you don't have to
understand the details of the memory
model if you wish to squeeze that last
little bit of performance out of the out
of the system it's something that you
then have to become more aware of
because you don't want to go to the
point where you're you're relying on
lucky timing in order for your program
to be correct and and that and that's
the danger when trying to optimize
concurrent programs you do things that
look like they might work or they look
like they should work but only according
to a night and
execution model an execution model of a
processor that is not like modern
processors those modern processors do
some downright weird things to your code
unless you tell them not to and the
primary way of telling them not to is to
use constructs like synchronization
right the most complicated part of the
memory model that people tend not to
realize is that it's not specifying what
effects synchronization operations have
on memory because that's true or people
have been doing that in different
systems for years it's easy to say if
you want this to work correctly you use
locks you use pthread mutex you have
condition variables and things like that
what the memory model has to do in Java
was provide the additional safety
guarantees that no matter how badly you
screw up the synchronization in your
program you are not going to be able to
break Java and you should not be able to
crash the VM you should not be able to
circumvent security mechanisms that are
inherent in the platform just because
you didn't use a lot correctly and you
know that's a very important thing if if
security can be circumvented just by
failing to acquire locks the right way
then then we don't have security at all
so the hardest part of the memory model
is actually coming up with these safety
guarantees it's you know it's providing
this safety net and so the basics the
basic rule that they came up with here
is they're not out of thin air rule it's
whenever you write a value to a memory
location or whenever when you every read
from a memory location you will get a
value that some thread at some point in
time actually wrote there yeah that's as
strong as it get you will not get
complete garbage you never see totally
random bits in rouen references and have
pointers that go off into the wild blue
yonder and so it sounds simple too to
say it that way actually specifying it
was an awful lot harder mm-hmm so let's
talk I mean that the stuff we talked
about until now is more or less
traditional concurrent programming with
locks and synchronization and it's
probably good practice among people who
know what they do in this area but there
is another approach of of concurrent
programming which where you'd find terms
like atomic variables and lock lock free
concurrent programming and things like
transactional memory so what is all that
stuff about how can you write concurrent
programs without locks after what we
discussed till now how does that work
that that's a very good question this is
all about performance because if flocks
were cheap and free right and we would
never have to worry about deadlocks we
always took care of deadlocks we
wouldn't worry about we would just use
them arbitrarily they would just be
taken for granted it just wouldn't be an
issue but locks do have a cost and we
can't avoid the fact there is a cost
there and whenever we use locking we are
reducing the availability of an object
or a service and a lot of people have
done a lot of research over the years I
mean over the last 50 years now that
there are ways of defining data
structures that can be safely mutated
and accessed concurrently that don't
require locks now unfortunately the
internals of these data structures do
not resemble your traditional notion of
a data structure in any way shape or
form
okay these are highly specialized data
structures that are operated on by
incredibly complex algorithms that
invariably rely on very specific memory
semantics things related to the memory
model so the basic ability to have some
kind of atomic operation that there are
some things you can rely on as being
indivisible execution units whether it's
some you know something that we all take
for granted that when you write to a
register on a machine that I'll write to
a memory location on machine that is an
indivisible unit of work yeah so the
idea is to have higher level things that
all are also indivisible like check and
act or something like that yeah you
can't get to you can't get very far with
only single reads and writes you had
some kind of read modify write see it is
exposed in some way by the hardware
platforms and and this is what's
happened you know ever since we've had
multiple systems we've had a mechanism
provided by different platforms to do
some kind of read modify write sequence
and one of the common ways that's
expressed this in a compare and set
operation right that you know if you you
read the value of some state and you
want to compute the next value of it and
then you want to replace the current
value with the next value as long as it
hasn't changed in the meantime here and
the hard part there is as long as it
hasn't changed in the meantime this is
the thing that you cannot you cannot
compose out of out of smaller primitive
there has to be some primitive atomic
operations provided to you and so if you
take an atomic atomic operation like a
parent said then you can build up these
algorithms and data structures to
provide a higher level totally
concurrent data structure like a
concurrent hash map and here people
could then use as a basic building block
on their application knowing that it's
completely thread safe it's also highly
performant but sometimes with a few
differences in semantics there you know
if you've relied on having exclusive
access to a data structure and then you
write one that's designed purely for
concurrent access then you've lost that
exclusivity if you happen to need it but
you get a lot of benefit from the high
performance that you now get from these
concurrent data structures mhm yeah and
you know in the research it even goes
even further if you've managed to come
up with a system that has a double
compare and set then the algorithms and
data structures get even simpler and you
can introduce much more of them but
unfortunately we don't have that in the
hardware right that's what I was going
to say that's a brook pass hardware
support and the more modern processors
probably have some level of support for
that so if you want to try and
generalize this then you start moving
into another realm and that's the realm
of transactional memory and
transactional transaction software
mm-hmm and I'll let Brian oily about
that yes so David talked about non
blocking algorithms these are algorithms
that use instead of using locks to
achieve safety use a finer grained
atomic instruction generally compare and
say a compare and swap load-linked store
conditional every processor offers one
of these and if writing correct programs
with locks is hard writing non blocking
algorithms is ten times harder that that
a lock free counter is trivial a lock
free stack is fairly straightforward
and when you get to something as complex
as a singly linked list where we're
talking about the level of effort of a
PhD thesis to prove that it's correct
okay so this is not something that the
average engineer on the street is going
to be coding on this weekend so
developing lock-free algorithms is
extremely difficult and is really the
purview of a very small group of experts
and so this is not really a viable way
to achieve better concurrent performance
only because so few people are going to
be able to use it
and the only way in which lock-free
algorithms are really going to provide
better system performance is to the
degree that they are encapsulated in
system libraries and and and much of the
performance improvements in the class
libraries going from Java 5 to Java 6
and Java 6 to Java 7 is the replacement
of lock lock based algorithm everyone's
huh but you asked about transactional
memory so transactional memory is a
concurrency control model that is still
squarely in the research phase and so
we're not going to be seeing systems
anytime soon and maintenance or
mainstream systems anytime soon that use
transactional memory but but the idea is
to allow the programmer to specify what
he wants not how he wants to do it so
I'm beginning an atomic operation do
this this this and that and now that our
atomic operation has ended and left the
system figure out the fastest way to
execute it and so we saw this with
databases exactly yeah originally
databases used very coarse-grained locks
that when you when one when one client
was was executing a transaction other
other clients might be locked out and
then databases got much smarter about
well this client is operating on this
data and that client is operate on that
data and I can allow both of these
transactions to proceed simultaneously
and similarly most of the time true
contention for data is limited and if
I'm working on this data structure over
here and you're one partition the data
structure then so you shouldn't have
locks for a whole hash table for example
about only four parts for it that's
that's right and and it's impossible to
do that with locks
it makes your algorithm more complicated
and so there's always this trade-off
between simplicity and performance
single coarse-grained lock is simpler
but offers worse scalability a larger
number of fine-grained locks offers
better scalability but more complexity
and higher risk of deadlock yeah and the
idea of transactions software
transactions is we're trying to
eliminate all that by letting the system
figure it out so rather than the program
are saying here is the the scope of
contention the data contention that I'm
concerned about you simply say I'm
starting an atomic operation now you go
and use some data and this
figures out well what did you touch oh
you only touch this one variable I can
execute this transaction concurrently
with these other transactions that
aren't touching those that variable and
McCann think about the promise of this
as being the same as the promise of
garbage collection
yeah annual memory management there's
all sorts of mistake modes the
programmer can make if they don't do it
correctly
whereas with garbage collection those
mistake modes go away the hope is that
with software transactions many of the
concurrent interactions like data races
and race conditions will go away as well
as far as how do we implement these
systems so that they work and so that
they are performant enough that we would
actually want to use them to write real
programs this is still a research area
so since we're already looking in the
future let's maybe look some more to
wrap this episode up so one thing I got
the impression during your tutorial and
also during other reading your book and
other discussions on concurrency my
impression very much is that current
languages such as Java including some of
the libraries in Java 5 the language
abstractions aren't good enough for
concurrency so you can't declaratively
specify for example I mean you can use
for example a Java annotation that says
you know this variable is guarded by
that lock but there is no way how the
compiler can easily verify that you
actually always hold the lock when you
access the variable so the point is do
you agree or do you think that that more
language support probably more
decorative support for concurrent
aspects of a program will make tool
support easier so that compilers or
other checkers can give you more more
meaningful messages about concurrency
problems you're probably about to code
in your in your code there's certainly
an opportunity there we always go
through these phases where we have the
mechanisms available to us and they are
extra linguae extra linguae mechanisms
that idioms basically that idioms
patterns use of libraries various
protocols and there is no built-in
support these are not part of a type
system they don't easily checked and the
next level is then to add some kind of
annotation that some other tool can use
to help to verify there are
tension is well what we coded was what
we intended to code yeah and there's
certainly a lot of benefit for doing
that if the tools were available today
they'd be helping Java programmers for
the next four or five years and there's
certainly a lot of there's some work
happening in that area to do that now
the bigger question there is is is going
back to the how we should be expressing
and modeling concurrency exactly not
programs yeah you know people there is a
long history of concurrency when Java
came along there are a few critics who
said you know 20 years within current
programming history and you know this is
the best they could come up and and that
is that fairly unfair because if you
look through the history of concurrent
programming you don't find any single
solution that stood out that Java could
have said hey yet this is obviously the
way to do concurrent programming there
are lots of individuals who think that
their way of doing concurrent
programming was the way to do concurrent
programming but there's certainly no no
obvious preeminent way to do it in that
space but the goal is always have been
to have these things be more decorative
you know what do I need to do not how do
I need to do with threads and locks is
all about how I have to do this
concurrent operation so if I want
concurrency I need threads if threads
are going to interact
I need synchronization I need locks it's
all about the mechanisms where we're
struggling at the language level with
the mechanisms yeah and what we would
like is something that simply says you
know do it you know even the do atomic
of software transactions is it's only
one level higher yeah because we still
need we're still responsible for
identifying where we need these
interactions to occur and the hope is
that eventually we will have
higher-level languages that can express
concurrency in in more succinctly search
projects people can look in tor well
there are different things I mean the
the fortress language that guys was
talking about this morning is a very
obvious concurrent parallel language but
its emphasis as you know all of the nice
neat decorative concurrent languages are
always to do with scientific programming
parallelism hmm it's not quite clear how
you use fortress to program your typical
middleware system doing you know
distributed client message
in various apps like that I'm not saying
it can't but it's certainly far more
obvious how to do parallel parallel loop
execution
running number crunching massively
parallel computing and that's always
been attention in this space so at this
stage I don't see anything on the
horizon for the for the environments in
which Java has currently been used to do
multi-threaded programming there have
been some attempts at various dialects
to sort of improve the model to make it
less less amenable to all the errors but
you always lose some some power and
flexibility in doing that so you know
I'm I don't think we're going to be out
of a job and teaching people another
another avenue for improving the quality
of concurrent programs is besides tools
and language support and all of that is
awareness that concurrent program is
simply is harder than that then
sequential programming and a big
challenge of that is just people
recognizing that and and to some degree
the java language plays a dirty trick on
programmers in that the the fundamental
values of the java language design are
simplicity and safety many features of
the language were designed to not allow
the programmer to turn off safety
guarantee you that it checks every
pointer for null when you do references
and it checks the the the bounds of an
array before you index into an array and
it checks the type of an object before
you cast it and you can't turn these
checks off the way that you could in you
know in previous languages so the idea
is we're offering a much higher level of
safety that if you do something wrong
we're gonna throw an exception we're not
gonna let you proceed with garbage data
and and and and similarly simplicity
we've take the language design takes
away many of the things that made a C++
more complicated being the obvious
example and then there's threads which
are neither simple nor safe that if you
have two threads access a variable
without synchronization you have data
race but it never throws data race
exception yeah
maybe does the wrong thing and so you
don't have that level of safety checks
working for you the way you do with
other mechanisms and and and the aspects
of failures and concurrent programs that
they're probabilistic events rather than
deterministic ones is something that
undermines a simplicity and so I think
part of it is simply recognizing that
when you're working in a concurrent
environment this is harder you need to
be more careful
you need to code more slowly carefully
review your code and have your code
reviewed by other people document your
design intent more and more clearly and
at the example that you gave about the
guarded by annotation yeah not only
might that be consumed by tools through
I'll you that you've made a mistake but
it's also a documentation thing that
tells you here's what I was thinking
when I was designing and just in case
I've forgotten between then and now and
and then it now might be only a few
hours or it might be six months when you
cut or a different person or a different
person when they come back to mint to
maintain the software and so realizing
that you're in a more dangerous more
hostile environment therefore you should
be more careful you know watch out for
the pitfalls work a little bit more
slowly not be afraid to ask someone to
peer review your code all of these
things while they're not magic bullets
and they're not technology solutions
they are effective ways to improve the
quality of concurrent programs okay so I
think that pretty much wraps it up
thanks for being on the show and yeah
looking forward to some additional book
on I don't know other advanced
comparative stuff thank you Marcus thank
you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details